Guide to the Stanford Center for Chicano Research Records
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stanford Center for Chicano Research records
1984-1998
SC0960
Stanford Center for Chicano Research
6 Linear feet
Records pertain primarily to the Ernesto Galarza Commemorative lecture series and the Galarza Prize for Excellence in Undergraduate or Graduate Research. Collection includes correspondence, committee records, publicity materials, invitations, text of lectures, papers submitted by students, clippings, photographs and other records. Also includes Armando Valdez’s report “A Study of Foundation Awards to Hispanic-oriented Organizations in the U.S.: 1981-1982,” March 1984.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Description of the Collection
Records pertain primarily to the Ernesto Galarza Commemorative lecture series and the Galarza Prize for Excellence in Undergraduate or Graduate Research. Collection includes correspondence, committee records, publicity materials, invitations, text of lectures, papers submitted by students, clippings, photographs and other records. Also includes Armando Valdez’s report “A Study of Foundation Awards to Hispanic-oriented Organizations in the U.S.: 1981-1982,” March 1984.
Access Terms
Stanford Center for Chicano Research; Mexican Americans --Research.; Mexican Americans.
Collection Contents
- Records, Accession ARCH-2009-204
  - Galarza-Paredes Paper 1986 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Galarza Lecture-1986 loose files (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Publication of Paredes Lecture 1986 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Cruz Reynoso Manuscript 1987 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Galarza Lectures-1987 loose files (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Galarza Commensurate Lecture Series 1987 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Galarza Lectures – Cruz Reynoso 1987 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Reynoso Manuscript 1987 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Galarza Manuscript-Reynoso 1987 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Galarza Lecture-1988 loose files (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Galarza Prize Papers 1988 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Galarza Prize 1988 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Galarza Lecture Nominating Committee 1988 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Tomas Atencio (present.) “Resolana’s pathway to knowledge” 5/13/88 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Galarza Lecture 1988 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Atencio Final Draft Galarza Lecture 1988 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Galarza Selection Committee 1988 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Letters of Intent for Galarza Prize 1988 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Tomas Atencio May 13th Galarza Lecture 1988 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Galarza Prize Papers 1988 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence Galarza Nominating Committee 1988 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Galarza Lectures 1988 loose files (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Galarza Prize Papers- Graduate 1988 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Galarza Lecture Selection Committee 1989 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Galarza Lecture-1989 loose files (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Galarza Prize 1989 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Letter of Intent 1989 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Herman Galegos-Galarza Lecture 6/2/89 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Galarza Prize-Undergraduate 1989 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Galarza Lecture 1990 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Galarza Selection Committee 1990 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Galarza Lecture-Islas Manuscript 1990 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Galarza Lecture-loose files 1990 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Galarza Prize-Information 1990 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Galarza Lecture-Letter of Intent 1990 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Galarza Lecture-Letter of Intent 1991 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Galarza Lecture-Invitations 1991 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Galarza Lecture-Posters 1991 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Galarza Invitations 1991 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Galarza Lecture-Announcements & Posters 1991 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Galarza Speaker Selection Committee 1991 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Galarza Project-Speaker Selection-Charlene Aguilar 1991 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Galarza Lecture-Papers 1991 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Galarza Lecture-Speaker: Polly Baca 1991 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Galarza Lecture-Papers 1991 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Galarza Papers-Instructions 1991 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Galarza Lecture-Research Competition 1991 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Galarza Prize 1991 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Galarza Lecture-Papers 1991 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Galarza-Grad Participants 1992 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Galarza Lecture-Graduate Acknowledgement of Intent Letter 1992 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Galarza-Grad Participants 1992 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Galarza Lecture-Graduate Papers 1992 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Julian Samora-Galarza Correspondence-Speaker 1992 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Galarza-Charlene’s Master File 1992 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Julian Samora Center Information 1992 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Galarza Lecture Faculty/Corp. Invites 1992 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Galarza Symposium San Jose State 1992 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Galarza Lectures-Posters/Announcements 1992 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Galarza-SCCR Advisory Board-Invitation to Corporations etc 1992 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Galarza Lecture-Julian Samora 1992 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Galarza Lecture Faculty Invitations 1992 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Galarza Lecture-General 1992 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Tamara’s Galarza File 1992 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Logos 1992 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Galarza Lecture-loose files 1992 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Galarza Prize-Undergraduate Letter of Intent 1992 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Galarza Lecture-Undergrad Acknowledgement of Intent Letter 1992 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Galarza Winning Papers 1992 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Galarza Undergraduate Papers 1992 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Galarza Advertising 1992 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Galarza Lecture Arrangements 1992 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Galarza-Antonia Hernandez, Speaker, Correspondence 1993 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Galarza-Charlene’s Master File 1993 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Galarza Lecture loose files 1993 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Galarza Undergraduate Prize Paper 1993 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Galarza Prize-Undergraduate Letter of Intent 1993 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Galarza Undergraduate Acknowledgement of Papers 1993 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Galarza Undergraduate Papers 1993 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Galarza Paper Competition Committee (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Galarza Graduate Papers 1993 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Galarza Graduate Prize Paper 1993 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Galarza Graduate Acknowledgement of Paper 1993 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Galarza Prize-Grad. Letter of Intent 1993 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Grad Entries T.Y. Letter 1993 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Galarza Advertising 1993 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Galarza Lecture Faculty Invitations 1993 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Special Invites to Galarza 1993 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Galarza Lecture SCCR Adv. Bd, Corp. Invites… 1993 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Galarza Lecture Corporate/Faculty Invites 1993 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Galarza News Reports 1993 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Galarza Purpose and Competition Proposal 1993 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Galarza Lecturer 1993 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Galarza Lecture Committee 1993 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Antonia Hernandez Galarza Speech ’92-‘93 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Galarza Lecture Arrangements 1993 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Galarza Lecture Background and Description 1993 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Galarza General Faculty Invites 1993 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Galarza Prize 1993 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Galarza Lecture loose files 1993 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Gabriela E. Corral “The Mexican Immigrant Experience…” 1994 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Irene Lara “A Chicana/o Literary Trajectory of Resistance” 1994 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Nancie Jarvis “Chicano Nationalism as Dynamic…” 1994 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Norma Mendoza-Denton “IntraEthnic and Interlinguistic…” 1994 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Tamara Alvarado et al “Drug Abuse in the East Palo Alto…” 1994 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Luz Elena Herrera “Latinos Respond to the Los Angeles Riots…” 1994 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Felipe Merino “An American Dream” 1994 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Henry D. Anaya “Hispanic Poverty: The Effect of Distinct…” 1994 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Ben V. Olguin “Enchando Madres: The Political and Symbolic…” 1994 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Kirsten Frohnmayer et al “Teen Pregnancy (from Under Pressure...” 1994 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Luis Millones “The Emancipatory Project of Tomas Rivera” 1994 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Molly Parker “Stigma and Chicana Teenage Pregnancy” 1994 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Rod Hernandez “Battling in LA: Chicano Graffiti Writing…” 1994 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Juan Jose Bueno “Exploitation and Acculturation in Mexico…” 1994 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Galarza Prize Selection Committee 1994 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Reminder Invitations for Special Guests at the Event 1994 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Computer Disk Directory Info 1994 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Letters of Intent-Undergrad 1994 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Letters of Intent-Grad 1994 (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Galarza Program 1994 (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Galarza Lecture & Reception Invitations 1994 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Galarza Speaker Selection Committee 1994 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Galarza Dinner Invitations & Responses 1994 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - SCCR Staff Meetings ’93-’94 re: Galarza (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Galarza Thank You Letters 1994 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Lecture Signs 1994 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Galarza Day of Event Checklist 1994 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Bustamante, Jorge 1994 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Galarza WTG Comp. Info 1994 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Galarza WTG Comp Ad 1994 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Galarza Prize Ltr of Acknowledgement for Students 1994 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Galarza Prize Letter of Acknowledgment for Sponsors 1994 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Galarza Press Conference 1994 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Galarza Advertising 1994 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Certificates for Galarza Prize and Arturo Islas Prize 1994 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Galarza 1994 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Galarza Lecture Publication 1986-1989 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Galarza Lecture Publication 1990-1992 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Galarza Lecture Publication 1993-1994 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Galarza Lecture 1994 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Galarza Speaker Selection Jorge Bustamante Corresp. 1994 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Galarza-Charlene’s Master File-Jorge Bustamante 1994 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Galarza Lecture loose files 1994 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Galarza Lecture loose files 1995 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Galarza-Charlene’s Master File-Amalia Mesa-Bains 1995 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Galarza Speaker Selection Amalia Mesa-Bains Corresp. 1995 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Galarza Prize Selection Committee 1995 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Galarza Certificates for Prize, Arturo Islas Prize 1995 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Galarza Lecture and Reception Invitations 1995 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Galarza Reminder Invitations Special Guests 1995 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Menus for Possible Galarza Dinner Sites 1995 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Amalia Mesa-Bains 1995 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Galarza Garden Court Hotel Correspondence and Info 1995 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Galarza SCCR Staff Meetings 1995 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Galarza Computer Disk Directory Info 1995 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Entertainment/Music 1995 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Galarza Program 1995 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Galarza Profile-Different Sizes for Programs/Certificates 1995 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Galarza Thank You Letters 1995 (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Galarza Writing Comp Info 1995 (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - Galarza Advertising 1995 (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - Galarza Writing Comp AD 1995 (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - Galarza Papers 1995 (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - Galarza Letters of Intent-Grad 1995 (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - Galarza Letters of Intent-Undergrad 1995 (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - Galarza Prize Letter of Acknowledgement Sponsors 1995 (Box 8, Folder 27)
  - Galarza Prize Letter of Acknowledgement Students 1995 (Box 8, Folder 28)
  - Galarza Undergrad/Grad Prize Winners 1995 (Box 8, Folder 29)
  - Galarza Prizewinners & Confidential Notes on Submissions 1995 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Galarza Lecture Assoc. Dir. Notes 1995 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Galarza Press 1995 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Galarza Guest List 1995 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Galarza Day of Event Checklist 1995 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Galarza Lecture Signs 1995 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Elba Romo “Curanderismo In A Society of Modern Medicine” 1995 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Jose J. Gonzalez “Divisions Within La Raza: A Preliminary…” 1995 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Ana Gonzalez “Mexican Female Workers: Impact of the…” 1995 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Lisa R. Gallegos “Heroes or Saints: Towards a Reformulation…” 1995 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Chiyuma Elliott “Writing Altarcitos: Representations of…” 1995 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Sonya Cotero “English as a Second Language Programs…” 1995 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Rosa Linda Armendariz “La Reina en Su Castillo de Cristal…” 1995 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Roxanna Vanessa Alvarado “Manuel Alvarado Almaguer …” 1995 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Gabriella Gutierrez “Altars: A Microcosm of Power or a…” 1995 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Marciala Gonzalez “Ruiz de Burton’s The Squatter and the Don…” 1995 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Michael E. Coke “Legal Classifications of the Chicano…” 1995 (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Simon Eduardo Weffer “Brown People Power: Disaggregation…” 1995 (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Maria Cotera “Reading Hybridity/Hybrid Reading” 1995 (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Galarza Speaker Selection Committee 1995 (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - Bert N. Corona – Vitae, 1996 (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - Lecture and Reception Invitations, 1996 (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Bert N. Corona Correspondence, 1996 (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - Program, 1996 (Box 9, Folder 24)
  - Guest List, 1996 (Box 9, Folder 25)
  - Entertainment/Music, 1996 (Box 9, Folder 26)
  - Writing Competition Information, 1996 (Box 9, Folder 27)
  - Letter of Acknowledgement Sponsors, 1996 (Box 9, Folder 28)
  - Graduate/Undergraduate Prize Winners, 1996 (Box 9, Folder 29)
  - Galarza Speaker Selection, 1996 (Box 9, Folder 30)
  - Speaker List, 1996 (Box 9, Folder 31)
  - Selection Committee, 1996 (Box 9, Folder 32)
  - Certificates for Prize, 1996 (Box 9, Folder 33)
  - Galarza Lecture loose files, 1996 (Box 9, Folder 34)
  - Manuel D. Ojeda “Understanding Homophobia Within The…”, 1996 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Marianna Diaz “From Consciousness Raising to …”, 1996 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Elsa R. Garcia “Latino Youth and Sport: A Positive Outlet for…”, 1996 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Jennifer Hill “Cuba Para Los Castros”, 1996 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Jennifer Hill “The Latin American Experience: Fact of Fiction”, 1996 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Ana Montano “Kettleman City: A Study of Environmental…”, 1996 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Alberto Rodriguez “Responsive Bilingual Education in…”, 1996 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Nereyda Salindas “Mexican & American Education: A Dual…”, 1996 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Articles – Bert Corona Spring, 1996 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Location, Date Selection, 1996 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Ads – Poster, 1996 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Invitations on behalf of Faculty, Mae Galarza Etc., 1996 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Josephina Fierro, 1996 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Dinner Invitations, 1996 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Prize Selection Committee, 1996 (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Galarza Volunteers, 1996 (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Galarza Speaker Selection Packet, 1996 (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - Speaker Correspondence, 1997 (Box 10, Folder 18)
  - Program, 1997 (Box 10, Folder 19)
  - Thank you letters, 1997 (Box 10, Folder 20)
  - Garden Court Hotel Correspondence & Info, 1997 (Box 10, Folder 21)
  - Entertainment/Music, 1997 (Box 10, Folder 22)
  - Reception-Catering, 1997 (Box 10, Folder 23)
  - Curtis Chen, 1997 (Box 10, Folder 24)
  - Menus, 1997 (Box 10, Folder 25)
  - Galarza Expenses, 1997 (Box 10, Folder 26)
  - Galarza Guest List, 1997 (Box 10, Folder 27)
  - Galarza Lecture Photos (J. Avila), 1997 (Box 10, Folder 28)
  - Speaker Vitae, 1997 (Box 10, Folder 29)
  - Ads-Poster, 1997 (Box 10, Folder 30)
  - Articles, 1997 (Box 10, Folder 31)
  - Galarza Expenses, 1997 (Box 10, Folder 32)
  - Writing Competition Information, 1997 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Letter of Acknowledgement/Sponsor, 1997 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Letter of Acknowledgement-Student, 1997 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Graduate/Undergrad Prize Winners, 1997 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Selection Committee, 1997 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Weffer, Simon “Legitimation, Adoption, and Reification…”, 1997 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Speaker Articles Spring, 1997 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Galarza Video, 1997 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Location, Date, Selection, 1997 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Invitations on Behalf of Faculty, Mae Galarza Etc., 1997 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Dinner Invitations, 1997 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Dinner-Entrée Etc. Selection, 1997 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Galarza Volunteers, 1997 (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - National Advisory Board Meeting 4/1997 (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Prize Selection Committee, 1997 (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - Certificates for Prize, 1997 (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - Paper for Certificates, 1997 (Box 11, Folder 17)
  - Gutierrez, Josef “MALDEF and the Struggle for Bilingual…”, 1997 (Box 11, Folder 18)
  - Ledezma, Maribel “Guillermo Gomez-Pena…”, 1997 (Box 11, Folder 19)
  - Medina, Sergio M. “Waking Up the Sleeping Giant”, 1997 (Box 11, Folder 20)
  - Romo, Elba “Perceptions of Mexican Popular Illnesses”, 1997 (Box 11, Folder 21)
  - Serrato, Gabriel A. “The Chicano Movement: Its Legacy…”, 1997 (Box 11, Folder 22)
  - Galarza loose files, 1997 (Box 11, Folder 23)
  - Speaker Correspondence, 1998 (Box 11, Folder 24)
  - Galarza loose files, 1998 (Box 11, Folder 25)
  - Galarza Lecture Expenses, 1998 (Box 11, Folder 26)
  - Ads/Press Releases, 1998 (Box 11, Folder 27)
  - Galarza Speaker Arrangements, 1998 (Box 11, Folder 28)
  - Galarza loose files, 1998 (Box 11, Folder 29)
  - Grad & Undergrad Prize, 1998 (Box 11, Folder 30)
  - Galarza Applicants, 1998 (Box 11, Folder 31)
  - Galarza Profile-Different Sizes for Programs and Certificates, 1998 (Box 11, Folder 32)
  - Galarza Lecture loose files, 1998 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Galarza Lecture (Vilma Martinez), 1998 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Galarza Archives-Photos, 1998 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Ernesto Galarza-Photos, 1998 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Faculty Photos, 1998 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Galarza Speakers, Guests, 1998 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Galarza Portrait, 1995, 1997 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Galarza, 1998 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Draft Given to SCCR by J. Bustamante, 1995 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - A Study of Foundation Awards, Armando Valdez (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Betacam Video recording of Ernesto Galarza Lecture, 4/24/1998 (Box 12, Folder 11)